Hey guys, Shandi said welcome back to
the channel and today we are going to
cover refresh scope and we have already
seen centralized configuration. So you
can say that this is the prerequisite.
Okay. So kindly check it out if you
haven't seen that. We have already done
setup of this central config files
config server and order service. We have
already done the setup of it and we
finished with asking one question that
hey let's say our order application is
running and someone has updated the
central config for order service. Do I
need to restart the app every time? What
I mean is that
during the application startup this
config server fetches the details from
the config file and save it. Similarly,
order service at the application startup
time fetch the property and save it.
Okay. But now when the application is
already in the running mode and somebody
changed this file, how it will get to
know that something has been changed.
Okay. So do we need to restart every
time? For now answer you I can say that
no. And it solution is at the rate
refresh scope. But let's try to
reproduce this scenario what we are
talking here. So say everything is same
what we have seen in the previous video.
I have a central config in the central
config order service D properties
currently it is this hello from order
div similar config server I have set up
this the same thing which we have set up
before you have dependency. You have
added this annotation you have added
application.properties properties file
properly. Okay. So this is also same no
change and then order service also
mostly same. You have the client config
dependency
application.properties also same. Okay.
The only difference I do here is that I
am using at the rate configuration
properties. If you remember from the
previous video we were having this.
Okay. We were having this uh so in the
controller order controller we were
reading the property like this from add
the rate value and the property name
which comes into this message and we are
using this we are printing it here.
Okay. But for this refresh scope instead
of using add the rate value I am using
add the rate configuration properties.
So we have also seen at the rate
configuration properties in dev. So
kindly check it out like how to use it.
Okay. But it's similar like it just take
out the property read the properties and
just convert it to POJO. Okay. So check
it out if you have any doubt with the
configuration properties topic. So the
same thing here if you see that I have
created one class order properties
and uh custom dossage is our property
name right? So there we have custom dot
message. Custom dot message is our
property name. So prefix is custom and
this field message. So custom dot
message. So that property will convert
it to this pojo. So it value is stored
into this field. Okay. The one question
might be coming at this place at your
time uh at your mind would be like why
why we are using at the rate
configuration properties for refresh
scope that I will tell you at end. Okay,
we when we will discuss the disadvantage
of refreshoscope there I will clear you
why I specifically use at the rate
configuration properties. Okay, but for
now there is no difference in the
behavior. If you want to use at the rate
value, you can use it. You will also get
the same output. If you want you can use
this at the rate configuration
properties also same output. Okay, the
only thing is that inside this message
field this property get mapped custom
dot message within
application.properties properties mapped
to this field. Okay. And this is just
nothing but a getter setter. And I'm
using this order properties here. Auto
add this.
And now I am using this order property
get message. Similarly earlier in the
controller itself I have this add the
rate value and using this. Now I since I
have this separate class okay which is a
pojo of the property. Now I have auto
added and it uses this
fetching the property like this right so
everything mostly same like what we have
done in previously now let's see now
let's start all the server I started the
config server and order server so my
config server started at 8888 my order
server is started at 80080
so first thing I invoke is /order/fetch
this controller /order
/f fetch. So it will print fetch order
and it will print the message of this
property. So currently our environment
is dev right. So it will fetch this
property hello from order dev.
So it will print
hello from order dev and currently
counter is one. We will also show you.
So currently this counter value is of no
use. I will show you like why I have
added it. Okay. Again in the end when we
will see the disadvantage. Okay. So
currently this is just for you can say
that uh no additional benefit here of
adding the counter for now at this point
of time. Okay. So
first thing first here is that when we
invoke the fetch endpoint we are able to
see that it is properly fetching the pro
uh properties from the central config.
Okay. Now let's update the central
config. Now I update this hello from
order dev to hello from order. This is
updated.
So I change this message value.
Now let's hit the order API again. I
called /order/fetch.
What you see
fetch order and message hello from order
tab old only. It's reading the old
property value only. even though the
property value is changed in the central
config repo.
Okay.
So this is the problem we are talking
about until and unless you won't restart
the order service again you will see
only the old value only. So how we can
resolve it? Refresh scope can help to
solve this. So what refresh scope does?
So this annotation
help to mark the bean which need to be
destroyed and recreated or you can say
that which need to be
dynamically
refreshed. So when we are saying that
hey it's refreshed actually it is doing
two things. it is first destroy the bean
and it create a new bean okay with the
latest value.
So now see this example
in the order properties right where I
have the configuration. So this is my
actually the property custom
dot
message. This is the property right
custom dot message. So custom dot
message will get ultimately mapped to
this field. Okay. So now and this is a
bean at the rate component. So now I
have marked at the rate refresh scope
here. So when I use add the rate refresh
scope over this bean I am telling a
spring boot that
this bean
add uh order properties say in this
scenario I am allowing it to dynamically
refresh.
Okay. And dynamically refresh means
whenever the refresh happens, it will
destroy the bean first, old bean first
and it will recreate a new one with the
latest value.
Okay, and how that refresh will happen.
Okay, it will happen
one way is through actuator.
Okay. So if you have not seen the
actuator video before, kindly check it
out because
this approach which I'm going to tell
you is use this actuator functionality.
So here if you remember if you recall
from the actuator video there is
something called custom actuator
endpoint like we can create our custom
endpoint through at the rate endpoint
annotation. Okay. So the same thing
spring cloud config has been used. So
spring cloud config has used this
property uh at the rate endpoint. So
here if you see this is the framework
code of the spring cloud config. So they
have a class refresh endpoint and they
have used this at the rate endpoint
refresh. So means they have exposed one
endpoint slash activuator
/ refresh
and internally here if you see they have
one write operation. So I told you right
we have already seen that in the
actuator what's right operation? So it's
a post kind of an endpoint. Okay. So
when with it is called with the post
this method will get invoked and what it
does it try to refresh. So it has logic
that if it is running
within a config server
then it fetch the property from the
central config. If this refresh endpoint
which has been invoked if this is
running inside a config client like
order service it will do two thing. It
will first invoke the config server,
fetch the property and then look for at
the rate refresh scope
beans. Okay. And then recreate them with
the fresh property value.
Okay. So you can say that the it depend
on the context where we are invoking
this endpoint. If you are invoking this
endpoint at config server then config
server task is to fetch the it will do
refresh is like fetch it from the
central config and if you are invoking
this endpoint in the client like order
it will call server config server first
f the endpoint and then all the beans
which are marked with refresh scope it
will recreate them that it will
Okay. So quickly
again is that at the red refresh scope
only task is to mark the bean which need
to be dynamically refreshed or
dynamically refreshed means the old bean
will get destroyed and new bean will get
created with the latest value. Okay. And
when when it when the dynamic refresh
will happen. Okay.
some refresh event has to be happen and
when that refresh event will happen we
have to invoke an endpoint in case we
are using the actuator approach.
Okay. And which endpoint actuator
exposes? So spring cloud config has
exposed this /actuator/refresh
and it does the
refresh or you can say that it creates a
refresh event. If the refresh event
happens within a config server,
you know that config server task is to
fetch from the
here we can see that config server task
is to fetch from the central config. So
that refresh will do. If you are
invoking the refresh at order service it
task is to call the config server fetch
it and all the beans which are marked
with at the rate refresh scope delete it
and create a new one.
Let's see that here now with an example.
Okay.
Now what to do that? All we need to do
is add the actuator dependency.
So in config server we have to add an
actuator dependency. So in the C we have
already seen that pom we have already
have the config server dependency. All
we are adding is actuator dependency.
Okay. And uh you know that from the
actuator video whenever there is an
endpoint we have to expose it. If you
are trying if you are planning to use
any actuator endpoint we have to expose
it. So I'm just exposing it.
Management.end endpoint. web this
endpoint I have to expose. Refresh.
Okay. You might be thinking what I'm
doing here why I'm going fast because we
have already seen this in the actuator
video. Everything is same. Okay. So we
are just exposing the refresh endpoint.
Okay. That's all we have to do in the
config server. Similarly in the order
micros service we already have the
dependency for the config client. All we
have to add is dependency for the
actuator and also we have to expose the
refresh endpoint because we are going to
invoke /actuator/ refresh here also.
Okay. And here
I mark the bean which I need to
dynamically refresh. So here this order
property bean
I want to dynamically refresh. So that's
why I marked it with at the rate refresh
scope. Okay. And no change in the
controller. So controller exposes /
order/fetch
endpoint.
Now let's see that I started the server
again. Okay. So first central config has
this uh changes order - service -.propy
current value is hello from order dev.
Okay. So this is the value currently
present. Okay. Now I started the config
server 8888. I started the order server
at 80080.
Now first I invoke /order/fetch.
Okay. It fetched the property properly
from the central config.
Hello from order defaf counter is one.
So you know that every time you hit by
default every class is single. Every
bean is single singleton. So whenever
you hit multiple time this counter I'm
just incrementing it just for proper
visualization.
So when you hit /order /f fetch it
properly fetch the property from the
central config.
Okay. So here our currently central
config has this hello from order dev. So
it properly fetch it. Now I am updating
the property in the central config. So I
change it from hello from order dev to
hello from order dev. This is updated to
test reference scope. So I just change
it.
Now I am hitting the order API again
/fetch.
So here if you see again the old value
hello from order dev. So you might be
saying hey sh now we have implemented uh
now we have annotated our bean with
refresh scope. We have added the
actuator dependency.
Why now it is coming as old? See
till now we have not invoked the refresh
event and refresh event will get occur
when we invoke this endpoint. Okay. So
now I am first invoking the endpoint
on config server and this is the
actuator endpoint right which is spring
cloud config exposed /actuator/refresh.
So I'm first invoking it on cloud config
server.
So when I did this it got success. What
it does? It calls the central config and
fetch the latest value. Now it fetch
this latest value.
Our config server goes to the central
config. Now fetch the latest server
latest property values.
Okay. So now my config server is
refreshed. Now the same API I'm invoking
on the order service. So now this is
8080 is my for order service I am
invoking /actuator / refresh. Now here
if you see that it shows the list of
you can say that the messages which are
refreshed which has it has fetched.
Okay. So custom dot message is the
endpoint right this custom dossage
because it has been changed. So it shows
that 200 it properly refresh this
property value.
Okay.
And notice that this is the post
operation. Why post operation? Because
in the framework if you see
there it uses the write operation.
That's why it is post. Okay. And this
endpoint / refresh we don't have to
create it already. Spring Cloud Config
does that for us. All we have to does is
that add the actuator dependency and
expose this refresh endpoint and just
invoke it to refresh it.
Okay.
So now my order service is also
refreshed. Now at after this now you
call /order/fetch.
Now you will see that you will get a
updated value. Hello from order dev.
This is updated to test refresh score.
Okay. So now it dynamically updated
without even restarting the application.
So counter value is three. Okay. So I
have not restarted it. Okay. So I just
hit it again. And if you see that it's
dynamically updated.
So it's clear.
So how we are dynamically updating
through with the help of actuator
endpoint.
Now let's come back to the point where
like we told that I am using
configuration properties.
Why I told you that when I'm saying that
dynamically refresh it does two thing it
destroy the bean and recreate it. So
when it when the old bean is destroyed
you will lose all the object state all
the work you have done on that object
that gone.
So that's why it's never recommended to
use refresh scope over controller
service. It's not safe. Okay. So you
know that from the over I like I've
already covered this at the red
configuration properties topic. So you
know that this on whichever the pojo
class we have write this at the rate
configuration properties or you can say
that in another term at the rate
configuration properties is a pojo which
only contains configuration. So it's
stateless only properties are there.
Okay. So this is safe
even it is dynamically refreshed means
it is destroyed old object old bean is
destroyed and new bean is created.
It's stateless. Okay. So that is okay.
That is safe. And you can understand
this with example. Let's say now if I
use refresh scope over a controller
class. Now see what happens. Why I use
configuring properties right? Why I use
configuration properties? Now let's say
the old way in the order controller
itself I have put refresh scope. And you
know that earlier in the central uh
configuration video we were using this
reading the property file like add the
rate value and using this message here
and I have a counter here just for the
better visualization.
Now I am using notice that I'm using
refresh scope over this controller.
Okay. Now first time you call at the
rate fetch uh /fetch.
So it will properly fetch the endpoint.
Hello from order dev properly. Okay.
Counter is one.
Now second time I am calling
counter is notice that counter is two
and same hello from order dev. Okay.
Currently I am not changing anything
into the central config but I invoke the
refresh endpoint at the order service.
Now what the refresh endpoint do
/actuator/ refresh now I'm calling it at
the client the uh configuration client
so it does two things first
fetch from
config server second
refresh
bean
with at the rate refresh scope. Okay. So
first it will try to fetch from the
config server like all the new value. So
it fetch it and second thing is like it
will try to update
all the beans which are marked with at
the rate refresh scope. Okay. So now
when I have done this so currently you
see empty here because uh here the old
value and the new value is same. So no
updation happened.
But again internally it has destroyed
the old bean created the new one but the
value is same it is not updated right so
that's why you see empty I haven't
changed the centralized uh central
config uh this property value
but it follow the proper sequence first
it might have called config server fetch
it and then it will dynamically refresh
means it deleted the old bean of which
one now the old bean of order controller
because refresh scope is used on top of
this bean.
So its object is old object old bean is
destroyed. It will create a new bean
with the new values.
Okay. So now when you try to invoke at
the rate fetch endpoint again.
Okay. So currently you will see the same
value because I haven't updated it. But
all I wanted to show is that see the
counter value. So counter value was two.
Now if you're invoking it again it
changed to one. Why?
Because when you have done refresh, it
deleted the old object old bean and
created a new fresh.
Okay. And you know that by default beans
are singleton. So it should goes to
three from two. Okay. But it creates a
new object that's why it is starting
with one. And that's why I that's the
reason I used add the rate configuration
properties
for the refresher scope. I don't want to
have a
recommend even this that use refresh
scope over the controller or service
layer never right because let's say your
controller class is taking a request and
suddenly somebody calls this
/actuator/refresh
that bean is destroyed your request will
be dropped
okay so again again very important in
interview als Also
never use at the refresh scope over a
controller or service. Always used over
a stateless object or stateless bean
like a POJO which is like for
configuration
right and one such is like add the rate
configuration properties. This is
nothing but a POJO for configuration
only. It's a stateless. It just have
property, configuration properties,
fields and values.
Okay.
Now one last question might have comes
to your mind. If you can think of it,
pause it and think it. What could be
that question? I'll tell you. Now till
now what we have seen that okay Shash
what we understood is that we have a
central config file. We have a config
server and we have different client like
order service. Let's say there are
hundreds of microservices.
Now if I have to dynamic refresh config
server without restarting this I invoke
actuator/refresh. Okay.
Now once this is refresh all these
clients need to be refreshed too. So I
need to invoke /actuator/refresh
on all these hundreds of microservices.
If we are using this approach/actuator
approach, yes, we have to call on all
this 100.
But yes, there is a different approach
too. In that approach, we only need to
refresh the config here.
And once the refresh happen here it will
publish you can say that a event or
message to all the clients that hey the
configuration is updated you guys also
update yourself
that can be happen through spring cloud
boss.
Okay that we will see next. So if so you
can say that that is another way of uh
making a refresh
event occur.
Okay. So you know that it's a two-step.
We have to mark the bean
and we have to mark the bean which need
to be dynamically refreshed and we the
marking of the bean happen to refresh
scope.
Now whenever the refresh event happens
all the beans which are marked as at the
refresh scope that will get refreshed.
Okay. So now this refresh event can
happen through actuator/refresh
endpoint which we have seen already and
another is through spring cloud boss. Uh
that's it for today. If you have any
doubt let me know. We can discuss
further. Bye.